Guide to Sommerreise in den Nahen Osten (Summer Trip to the Near East) AD.MC.042
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Sommerreise in den Nahen Osten (Summer Trip to the Near East)
August 1966
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Fischer, Paul
AD.MC.042
130 Photographic Prints The album measures album 26 x 26 cm, each photograph around 7.7 x 10.5cm. Photographs all in good condition, a few are missing. The album has damage to the spine but not to the binding.
An album of 130 images taken during a trip through Lebanon, Syria, Jordan and Palestine in August 1966. Images are focussed on historical and religious sites, the final few pages appear to be taken in Germany. The album was compiled by Paul Fischer. Fischer was a (German) soldier in World War I who worked on the Berlin–Baghdad railway (Bagdadbahn) for the firm Philipp Holzmann (Frankfurt am Main). After World War I he was a prisoner of war (Kriegsgefangener) in Turkey, after his release and back in Germany he married Anna Liebing (maiden name) in 1.10.1927. He died in East Germany.
Box 042
Content Description
An album of 130 images taken during a trip through Lebanon, Syria, Jordan and Palestine in August 1966. Images are focussed on historical and religious sites, including Beiteddine Palace, Baalbek, the Umayyad Mosque, Dome of the Rock, Al-Aqsa Mosque, walls of Jerusalem and Abbey of the Dormition. There are also views of markets, buildings, landscapes and local populations. The final few pages appear to be taken in Germany.
Biographical / Historical
The album was compiled by Paul Fischer. Fischer was a (German) soldier in World War I. From 1916-1919 he wporked as an Eisenbahn-Pionier. In this time he worked on the Berlin–Baghdad railway (Bagdadbahn) for the firm Philipp Holzmann (Frankfurt am Main). After World War I he was a prisoner of war (Kriegsgefangener) in Turkey, after his release and back in Germany he married Anna Liebing (maiden name) in 1.10.1927 and lived in Penig, Saxony. Later he worked at the Adolph Oeser, Maschinenfabrik in Leipzig, until 1940. Between 1941-1945 he worked in the Getriebewerk (transmission plant) in Penig. He died in East Germany.
Arrangement
Collection was processed in order that it was recieved
Conditions Governing Access
No restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Frank Schulze, Heimstättenstraße 43 09217 Burgstädt/Herrenhaide E-Mail: don-knarf@web.de Fax: 03724/668598 Tel.: 0173/3511052. Prior provenance unknown.
Lebanon; Syria; Jordan; Photographic Prints; Landscapes; Architecture
- The front cover of the album Sommerreise in den Nahen Osten (Summer Trip to the Near East), August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref1; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Syria; Lebanon; Jordan
- The inside front cover of the album Sommerreise in den Nahen Osten (Summer Trip to the Near East), August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref2; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
- Portraits of two men standing in front of a Middle East Airlines, Air Liban plane., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref3; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  German Writing; Airplanes; Airports; Individual Portraits; Transportation; Men; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Arabic Writing; Unknown Locations
- From the top down: One Lebanese pound note, two views of mountains, and two views of buildings in Lebanon., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref4; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Money; Lebanon; Mountains/Hills; Buildings; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Women; Forest/Woodlands; Outdoors; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; French Writing; Arabic Writing
- From the top left clockwise: A group portrait of several boys, a man standing next to an automobile, two boys facing away from the camera with a group of men and children sitting with sheep in the background, and a street scene in which man holds a bottle up in the foreground (linked ref6)., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref5; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Drinks/Beverages; Sheep; Animals; Buildings; Streets/Roads; Regional/National Dress; Boys; Children; Men; Women; Arabic Writing; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Lebanon; Streets/Roads
- Left: a boy standing near an automobile, two men ride horses in the background. Right: a portrait of a man sitting next to a cactus (linked ref5)., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref6; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Head Covers/Veils; Individual Portraits; Women; Men; Regional/National Dress; Horses; Animals; Boys; Children; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Buildings; Streets/Roads; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Group Portraits; Outdoors; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Lebanon
- A portrait of a man wearing a head covering., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref7; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Men; Individual Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Head Covers/Veils; Streets/Roads; Women; Bags/Purses; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Lebanon
- From the top left clockwise: Views of the Beiteddine Palace including a fountain in the courtyard, an interior, and an interior with inlay decorations., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref8; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Beit ed-Dine, Lebanon; Palaces; Fountains; Buildings; Architecture; Furnishings; Shisha/Hookah/Nargiles; Lanterns/Lamps; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints
- Top: A sword encased in glass. Bottom: A fountain in Beiteddine Palace., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref9; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
- Views of ruins in Baalbek, Lebanon., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref10; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; Mountains/Hills; Construction; Men; Regional/National Dress; Buildings; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Baalbek, Lebanon; German Writing
- Views of columns in Baalbek, Lebanon., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref11; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Architecture; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Construction; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Baalbek, Lebanon
- From the top left clockwise: two columns, a facade of a building, three men sitting outdoors, one plays an instrument, and a domed building., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref12; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Shisha/Hookah/Nargiles; Regional/National Dress; Carpets/Rugs; Furnishings; Men; Group Portraits; Facial Hair; Buildings; Architecture; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Prayer Beads; Street Vendors; Musical Instruments; Workers; Tea/Coffee; Drinks/Beverages; String Instruments; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Baalbek, Lebanon
- Three views of architectural details and one view of a row of columns in Baalbek, Lebanon., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref13; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Baalbek, Lebanon; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; Buildings; Cars/Trucks; Transportation
- Portraits of men in Damascus, Syria., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref14; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Men; Regional/National Dress; Individual Portraits; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; German Writing; Streets/Roads; Arabic Writing; Signs/Signposts; Shops; Markets; Food; Facial Hair; Buildings; Head Covers/Veils
- Street views of Damascus, Syria, including portraits of a fruit vendor, children, and men., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref15; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Workers; Food; Markets; Regional/National Dress; Street Vendors; Streets/Roads; Goats; Animals; Shops; Individual Portraits; Men; Group Portraits; Boys; Children; Girls; Head Covers/Veils; Buildings; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Facial Hair; Architecture
- From the top left clockwise: A portrait of a crying girl, a child, a boy selling food, and a view of the Basman Hotel., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref16; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Workers; Food; Boys; Girls; Children; Streets/Roads; Street Vendors; Markets; Hotels; English Writing; Signs/Signposts; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Individual Portraits; Buses; Shops
- Street scenes in Damascus, including views of Martyrs' Square and the Telegraph Monument., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref17; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Buildings; Monuments/Memorials; Architecture; Streets/Roads; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Mountains/Hills; Men; Bicycles/Tricycles; Street Lamps; Boys; Girls; Children; Group Portraits; Buses; Statues/Sculptures
- From the top left clockwise: buildings in Damascus, a street scene, a group portrait of six men, and The Minaret of the Bride (Madhanat al-Arus) on the Umayyad Mosque., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref18; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Damascus, Syria; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Buildings; Architecture; Umayyad Mosque/Great Mosque of Damascus; Religious Sites; Mosques; Streets/Roads; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Group Portraits; Men; Boys; Children; Facial Hair; Signs/Signposts; Arabic Writing; Advertisements; Mountains/Hills; Buses
- Views of the Hamidiyah Souq, including a glass dealer, a fruit vendor, and a tram., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref19; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Markets; Shops; Regional/National Dress; Smoking; Cigarettes; Crowds; Street Vendors; Workers; Men; Group Portraits; Food; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Streets/Roads; Buildings; Trams; Arabic Writing; Hats; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Boys; Girls; Children; Women; Facial Hair
- From the top left clockwise: one view of the Hamidiyah Souq, and views of other markets in Damascus., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref20; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Markets; Shops; Street Vendors; Workers; Streets/Roads; Buildings; Food; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Umbrellas/Parasols; Donkeys; Animals; Buses; Group Portraits; Men; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Crowds; Regional/National Dress; Carriages/Coaches; Bicycles/Tricycles; Boys; Children; Facial Hair; Hats; Signs/Signposts
- From the top left clockwise: two street views, and two views of the Hamidiyah Souq, Damascus., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref21; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Markets; Shops; Street Vendors; Streets/Roads; Women; Boys; Girls; Children; Group Portraits; Head Covers/Veils; Facial Hair; Men; Individual Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Buses; Donkeys; Animals; Transportation; Umbrellas/Parasols; Hats; Buildings; Bicycles/Tricycles; Cars/Trucks
- Portraits of groups in a market, Damascus., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref22; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Food; Street Vendors; Markets; Shops; Workers; Boys; Children; Regional/National Dress; Buildings; Horses; Animals; Transportation; Women; Head Covers/Veils; Hats; Facial Hair; Group Portraits; Mosques
- From the top left clockwise: a group of men in a butcher's shop, street scenes and people walking in front of Basman Hotel in Damascus., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref23; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Bags/Purses; Head Covers/Veils; Women; Men; Street Vendors; Food; Hotels; English Writing; Signs/Signposts; Streets/Roads; Workers; Hats; Uniforms; Animals; Buildings; Mountains/Hills; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Bicycles/Tricycles; Donkeys; Boys; Children; Group Portraits; Meat; Facial Hair
- From the top left clockwise: street vendors and people in a market, a crowd in the market, the Umayyad Mosque, and a mosque in Damascus., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref24; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Umayyad Mosque/Great Mosque of Damascus; Mosques; Religious Sites; Buildings; Architecture; Markets; Women; Head Covers/Veils; Group Portraits; Men; Regional/National Dress; Hats; Bicycles/Tricycles; Arabic Writing; Transportation; Cars/Trucks; Construction; Workers; Shops; Street Vendors; Children; Boys
- From the top left clockwise: buildings and a minaret, an altar in the Church of Saint Catherine, a statue in the Church of Saint Catherine's courtyard, and a man walking in the street in front of Bab Kisan., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref25; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Architecture; Churches; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Damascus, Syria; Mosques; Buildings; Religious Sites; Religious Crosses; Statues/Sculptures; Streets/Roads; Men; Individual Portraits; Cameras; Hats
- Left: A aerial view of people and cars in the street next to the Basman Hotel. Right: A man standing next to a road., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref26; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Damascus, Syria; Hotels; Signs/Signposts; English Writing; Men; Boys; Children; Streets/Roads; Donkeys; Buildings; Regional/National Dress
- From the top left clockwise: an encampment in the desert, a portrait of a boy in front of a terraced city, and two views of camels in the desert, Jordan., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref27; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Jordan; German Writing; Camels; Animals; Women; Head Covers/Veils; Boys; Children; Mountains/Hills; Buildings; Architecture; Tents; Individual Portraits; Deserts
- Views of rocky landscapes, mountains, and a camel caravan in the desert, Jordan., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref28; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Jordan; Mountains/Hills; Landscapes; Deserts; Camels; Animals; Streets/Roads
- Camels and donkeys in the desert, Jordan., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref29; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Jordan; Mountains/Hills; Deserts; Camels; Donkeys; Animals; Streets/Roads; Tents
- Top-left clockwise: a view of three structures in the desert, buildings on terraced hillsides, houses on a terraced hillside, houses on a terraced hillside in Bethlehem., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref30; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Buildings; Mountains/Hills; Jordan; Deserts; Architecture; Landscapes; Palestine; Bethlehem; Houses; Construction
- From the top left clockwise: the Dome of the Rock and Jerusalem, the Al-Aqsa Mosque, walls of Jerusalem and Abbey of the Dormition (background), a rocky outcrop and a portrait of two boys on the road overlooking Bethlehem., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref31; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Jordan; Jerusalem; Palestine; Al-Aqsa Mosque/al-Masjid al-ʾAqṣā; Dome of the Rock/Qubbat al-Sakhrah; Mosques; Religious Sites; Streets/Roads; Temple Mount/al-Ḥaram al-Šarīf; Churches; Caves; Buildings; Architecture; Boys; Children; Group Portraits; Mountains/Hills; Church of the Nativity; Bethlehem
- From the top left clockwise: a hotel lobby desk, tents by a road, a boy running on the road, and a portrait of a man wearing an agal and keffiyeh, standing against a wall., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref32; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Palestine; English Writing; Regional/National Dress; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Facial Hair; Men; Boys; Children; Streets/Roads; Individual Portraits; Hotels; Tents; Buildings; Furnishings; Deserts; Mountains/Hills
- From the top left clockwise: a man standing on a ledge in front of a rock formation with rock-cut tombs; people in front of the Golden Gate, Jerusalem; and a man posing in front of the River Jordan., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref33; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Jordan; Gethsemane, Jerusalem; Gardens; Parks; Jerusalem; Palestine; Mountains/Hills; Religious Sites; Men; Individual Portraits; Rivers; Jordan River; Tombs/Mausoleums; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Hats; Regional/National Dress; Golden Gate, Jerusalem; Cemeteries; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts
- A portrait of a man standing in a body of water., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref34; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Palestine; Men; Individual Portraits; Water; Bathing Suits/Swimsuits; Swimming; Seas; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Mountains/Hills
- Top: an olive tree in the Garden of Gethsemane. Bottom: two views of men and women beside the outside wall of the Church of the Nativity, Bethlehem., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref35; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Bethlehem; Jerusalem; Gethsemane, Jerusalem; Palestine; Men; Women; Regional/National Dress; Group Portraits; Outdoors; Gardens; Parks; Religious Sites; Church of the Nativity; Churches; Streets/Roads; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Canes/Walking Sticks
- A blank page in the album 'Travel in the Middle East.', August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref36; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Syria; Lebanon; Jordan; Palestine
- Top: a view of the ship 'Abisko Stockholm.' Bottom: a view of the ship 'Fleethorn, Kiel(?), August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref37; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Unknown Locations; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Water; Flags; Docks/Piers/Jetties
- Portraits of men and women in a kitchen (linked ref40, ref41, ref42)., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref38; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Women; Men; Individual Portraits; Tea/Coffee; Drinks/Beverages; Germany; Furnishings
- A blank page in the album 'Travel in the Middle East.', August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref39; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
- Clockwise from bottom-left: two portraits of the same man, a man sitting outdoors, a portrait of two people kissing (linked ref38, ref41, ref42)., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref40; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Germany; Color Photography; Kissing; Men; Women; Group Portraits; Individual Portraits; Drinks/Beverages; Alcohol; Jewelry; Furnishings; Facial Hair; Handkerchiefs /Pocket Squares; Outdoors; Coast
- Two portraits of the same man (linked ref38, ref40, ref42)., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref41; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Germany; Furnishings; Men; Individual Portraits
- Two portraits of the same man (linked ref38, ref40, ref41)., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref42; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Men; Individual Portraits; Pens/Inkwells; Furnishings; Germany
- A portrait of a woman sitting on an armchair (linked ref38)., August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref43; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Furnishings; Women; Individual Portraits; Germany; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Carpets/Rugs
- A blank page in the album Sommerreise in den Nahen Osten (Summer Trip to the Near East), August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref44; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
- The inside back cover of the album Sommerreise in den Nahen Osten (Summer Trip to the Near East), August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref45; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
- The back cover of the album Sommerreise in den Nahen Osten (Summer Trip to the Near East), August 1966; AD_MC_042_ref46; Fischer, Paul; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 042)
  Syria; Lebanon; Palestine; Jordan